Guide to the R. B. Holmes Photograph Collection, 1910-1926 and undated RL.00565
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
R. B. Holmes photographs
1910-1926 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
Holmes, Randolph Bezant, 1888-1973
RL.00565
7.6 Linear Feet 208 items
The images in the collection were taken by British photographer R. B. (Randolph Bezzant) Holmes and possibly others from his studio who traveled with him. Holmes was the owner of the R. B. Holmes & Co. photography studio in Peshawar, Pakistan. Of the 208 prints in the collection, one hundred two are loose, 11.5 x 9.5" black-and-white photographic prints of Afghanistan, India, and Pakistan. The remaining 106 prints are mounted in three commercial albums whose subjects range widely, from Afghan War-period images of the Khyber Pass, Landi Khana, Ali Musjid, and the Kabul River; to pastoral scenes around Nowshera, street scenes in Peshawar city, and panoramic views of the Peshawar Valley, to views from India, including the Jhelum and Liddar valleys, Srinagar, lower Himals, Harabal waterfall, Shalimar, and the Taj Mahal in Agra, to images of Waziristan and the Khyber railway. The sizes of the mounted prints range from 8.25"x5.75" to 11.25"x9", along with some panoramic prints. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The R. B. Holmes Afghan War Photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase from 2009-2011, 2014, and 2016.
Biographical Note
Randolph Bezzant Holmes was born in 1888. He was a commercial photographer who took over the business established by his father, William D. Homes, around 1899 in Peshawar, Pakistan. Holmes was an official photographer of the Afghan Wars on the North West Frontier in Afghanistan. He also spent time in Kashmir and in other Asian locales. Later in life he also painted watercolor landscapes from the same areas. In 1929 he published a memoir of his time in Afghanistan, Story of the North West Frontier Province, Peshawar, containing gelatin print plates of his landscapes. Holmes died in 1973.
Collection Overview
Of the 208 prints in the collection, one hundred two are loose, 11.5 x 9.5" black-and-white photographic prints of Afghanistan, India, and Pakistan. The majority of these detailed images were taken during the end of the Anglo-Afghan war in 1919 and depict large British military camps and vast landscapes, sometimes with camel caravans or military convoys. Some scenes show the remains of villages, military features such as towers, and religious structures. There are portraits of individuals, including camel drivers, a sniper, a female spinner, a young woman dressed in traditional wear, and various groups. The landscape views include the Khyber Pass, Tanai Gorge, Kabul River, Khargali Ridge, Dal Lake, Nanga Parbat, and the Sikkim Himalaya. Military camp views, many in panoramic scale with fine detail, include Landi Khana, Dakka Plain, and Landi Kotal.
The remaining 106 prints are mounted in three commercial albums whose subjects range widely, from Afghan War-period images of the Khyber Pass, Landi Khana, Ali Musjid, and the Kabul River; to pastoral scenes around Nowshera, street scenes in Peshawar city, and panoramic views of the Peshawar Valley, to views from India, including the Jhelum and Liddar valleys, Srinagar, lower Himals, Harabal waterfall, Shalimar, and the Taj Mahal in Agra, to images of Waziristan and the Khyber railway. The sizes of the mounted prints range from 8.25"x5.75" to 11.25"x9", along with some panoramic prints. There are 12 gelatin silver prints. The images of Waziristan (Box 6) are out of copyright. There are also several photographs from the Diwan and Mela Ram studios in the Waziristan images. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts.
Related Material
R. B. Holmes Collection (papers and photographs)
Macmillan Brown Library, University of Canterbury, New Zealand
Afghan Wars; Afghan Wars -- Pictorial works; Afghanistan -- Pictorial works; Afghanistan -- Social conditions -- 20th century; India -- Pictorial works; India -- Social conditions -- 20th century; Pakistan -- Pictorial works; Pakistan -- Social conditions -- 20th century; Photograph albums; Black-and-white photographs; Platinum prints; Gelatin silver prints; Waziristan (Pakistan) -- Pictorial works; Great Britain. Army -- History -- 20th century; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Holmes, Randolph Bezant, 1888-1973; R. B. Holmes & Co. (Peshawar)
- Photographic Prints, 1910-1926 and undated; 1
  - Jamrud Fort and entrance to the Khyber Pass., 2 copies (Box 1, Print 1)
    Scope and Contents
    One copy housed with Print 9
  - Entering the Khyber Pass. Camel Convoy. (Box 1, Print 2)
  - Ali Musjid Camp. (Box 1, Print 3)
  - Ali Musjid Camp., 2 copies (Box 5, Print 3, Page 2)
    One copy housed with Print 35
  - Exit of the Khyber into the Peshawar Plains. (Box 1, Print 4)
  - Looking North through the Gorge at Ali Musjid., 2 copies (Box 1, Print 5)
    One copy housed with Print 15
  - Looking North through the Gorge at Ali Musjid. (Box 5, Print 5, Page 1)
  - Looking South through the Gorge at Ali Musjid. (Box 1, Print 6)
  - Camp at Landi Kotal (left half of panorama). (Box 1, Print 7)
  - Camp at Landi Kotal (right half of panorama). (Box 1, Print 7a)
  - Looking towards the water works on the road to Landi Khanna. (Box 1, Print 9)
    Housed with Print 32
  - On the road to Landi Khana looking towards Kbargali ridge. (Box 1, Print 11)
    Caption on photograph reads "The Tangi Gorge."
  - On the road to Landi Khana looking towards Kbargali ridge. (Box 5, Print 11, Page 5)
  - Looking through the Tytler Gorge towards Landi Khanna. (Box 1, Print 15)
  - Looking through the Tanai Gorge towards Landi Khanna. (Box 1, Print 16)
  - Khargali Ridge and Bagh (left half of panorama). (Box 1, Print 18)
  - The Double road to Landi Khana. (Box 5, Print 19, Page 7)
  - From Kafirkote over looking the Khargali Ridge. The battle-ground of the 11th May 1919, Bagh Springs and village in the distance and remains of old Budhist Stupa on extreme left. (Box 1, Print 20)
  - From Kafirkote towards Dakka. Kabul river in the distance and remains of old Grecian Fort wall on near hill. (Box 1, Print 21)
  - From Karfirkote towards Dakka. Kabul river in the distance and remains of old Grecian Fort wall on near hill. (Box 5, Print 21, Page 8)
  - Entering the Dakka Plain. (Box 1, Print 22)
  - Untitled. Dakka camp, Kabul River? (Box 1, Print 25)
  - Untitled. Dakka camp, Kabul River? (Box 1, Print 25a)
  - Dakka camp, Kabul River. (Box 1, Print 26)
  - Dakka camp showing Fort Robart and Kabul river. (Box 1, Print 27)
  - Looking across the Kabul river, showing ferry. (Box 1, Print 31)
  - After bombardment view of Loe Dakka and the main road showing deserted villages towards Landi Khana. (Box 1, Print 32)
  - A view of villages in the Khyber. (Box 1, Print 35)
  - Looking towards Jallalabad. Taken from a picquet during an engagement., 2 copies (Box 1, Print 37)
  - Tribal towers and villages. (Box 1, Print 51)
  - A general view of Ali Musjid from the fort., 2 copies (Box 1, Print 58)
  - Looking down through the Gorge towards Ali Musjid. (Box 5, Print 61, Page 4)
  - Khyber Pass near Landi Khana (Box 5, Print 66, Page 6)
  - Landi Khana and tribal villages. (Box 1, Print 70)
  - Khyber Pass near Landi Khana., 2 copies (Box 1, Print 73)
  - In the Tank Zam looking towards Kirgi. (Box 6, Print 81, Page 38)
  - [Convoy in Taki Zam.] (Box 6, Print 83, Page 37)
  - In the Hingis Tangi. (Box 1, Print 84)
  - In the Hingis Tangi. (Box 6, Print 84, Page 39)
  - Looking across the Tank Zam towards Jandola. (Box 1, Print 85)
  - Looking across the Tank Zam towards Jandola. (Box 6, Print 85, Page 41)
  - Camp Kotkai. (Box 6, Print 86, Page 35)
    Hand tinted
  - Looking towards Kotkai from the Ahnai Tangi. (Box 6, Print 87, Page 40)
  - Entering the Ahnai Tangi. (Box 1, Print 88)
  - Entering the Ahnai Tangi. (Box 6, Print 88, Page 36)
  - Looking through the Ahnai Tangi (near). (Box 1, Print 89)
  - View from Piaza Raghza towards Pir Gul. (Box 1, Print 92)
  - View from Piaza Raghza towards Pir Gul (Box 6, Print 92, Page 34)
  - Mahsud and Waziri Spies. (Box 6, Print 94, Page 1)
  - Typical Mahsuds. (Box 6, Print 96, Page 5)
  - Tribesmen leaving a Jirga at Kaniguram. (Box 1, Print 97)
  - Jirga with Kaniguram in back ground. (Box 1, Print 98)
  - Jirga with Kaniguram in background. (Box 6, Print 98, Page 12)
  - Battery coming into action below tribal fortified tower. (Box 1, Print 100)
  - Mountain Battery going into action, showing a cave dwelling. (Box 6, Print 101, Page 42)
  - Derajat column in camp at Laddha. (Box 1, Print 102)
  - Kaniguram. (Box 6, Print 107, Page 33)
  - Kaniguram camp with Gurkha picquet in foreground. (Box 6, Print 108, Page 32)
  - Gurkhas camp under snow. (Box 6, Print 109, Page 31)
  - Kaniguram picquets under snow. (Box 1, Print 110)
  - Isha Post, on the road to Miranshah. (Box 6, Print 113, Page 3)
  - Waziri caravan types. (Box 2, Print 114)
  - The Waziri., 2 copies (Box 2, Print 117)
  - "Even to this.", 2 copies (Box 5, Print 119, Page 18)
  - The Old Pathan. (Box 2, Print 122)
  - A Pathan Woman. (Box 2, Print 124)
  - A Tribesman of the Border. (Box 2, Print 125)
  - Two Afghans. (Box 2, Print 126)
  - Two Afghans with their camels. (Box 2, Print 127)
  - Persian Wheel, Nowshera. (Box 5, Print 128, Page 17)
  - Kabul river and Bridge of boats, Nowshera, (Sunrise). (Box 5, Print 129, Page 16)
  - The Sniper. (Box 2, Print 131)
  - Afridi Man. (Box 2, Print 131a)
  - Pathan woman spinning. (Box 2, Print 132)
  - Jhelum Valley Road and River. (Box 5, Print 155, Page 24)
  - Srinagar, looking from the Sheikh Bagh towards the Thakt-i-Sulieman. (Box 5, Print 158, Page 28)
  - A scene in Srinagar City. (Box 5, Print 159, Page 27)
  - View entering Srinagar by river. (Box 5, Print 160, Page 25)
  - On the Dal Lake, Srinagar. (Box 2, Print 161)
  - Kashmiri Women Pounding Rice (Box 2, Print 164)
  - Gulmarg, showing the Club, Church and Pologround. (Box 5, Print 165, Page 35)
  - Camping ground at Sonemarg, beneath the Glaciers. (Box 5, Print 169, Page 40)
  - Looking from Zojila to Baltal, 1,500 feet below. (Box 2, Print 170)
  - Looking from Zojila to Baltal, 1,500 feet below. (Box 5, Print 170, Page 41)
  - Camping ground at Panjitarni, one march before Amarnath. (Box 2, Print 174)
  - Lake Gangabal and Mount Haramouk. (Box 5, Print 175, Page 39)
  - By Tannin River and Mountain heights in mist. (Box 2, Print 180)
  - By Tannin River and Mountain heights in mist. (Box 5, Print 180, Page 36)
  - Harabal Waterfall. (Box 5, Print 182, Page 38)
  - Nishat Bagh. (Box 5, Print 184, Page 32)
  - Poplar Avenue (Box 5, Print 193, Page 23)
  - Chenar Bagh. (Box 5, Print 194, Page 29)
  - General view in the Liddar Valley. (Box 5, Print 207, Page 43)
  - Pastoral scene at Aro, Liddar Valley. (Box 2, Print 209)
  - Liddar stream, Kolahoi peak in the background. (Box 5, Print 210, Page 42)
  - Sind river and heights, one march before Sonemarg. (Box 5, Print 212, Page 37)
  - Gulmarg in autumn. (Box 5, Print 215, Page 33)
  - Pines Gulmarg. (Box 5, Print 220, Page 34)
  - Shalimar. (Box 5, Print 233, Page 31)
  - Shalimar. (Box 5, Print 234, Page 30)
  - Srinagar City. (Box 5, Print 240, Page 26)
  - Parachinar Bazar. (Box 2, Print 260)
  - Parachinar Dak Bungalow. (Box 5, Print 263, Page 19)
  - Deserted tribal fort near Guja Chinar in the Spin Tangi. (Box 2, Print 268)
  - Kurram Militia Post. (Box 2, Print 269)
  - Looking towards Kohat from the Pass. (Box 6, Print 277, Page 13)
  - A defile in the Kohat Pass. (Box 2, Print 279)
  - Looking down on Kala Bagh and Mari Indus. (Box 2, Print 300)
  - Looking towards Khirgi from Manzai. (Box 2, Print 301)
  - Looking towards Khirgi from Manzai. (Box 6, Print 301, Page 57)
  - Village tower by Jandola. (Box 2, Print 303)
  - Jandola Fort. (Box 2, Print 304)
  - Jandola Camp. (Box 2, Print 305)
  - Jandola Camp. (Box 6, Print 305, Page 56)
  - In the Shahur Tangi. (Box 2, Print 306)
  - In the Shahur Tangi. (Box 6, Print 306, Page 45)
  - Exit of the Shahur Tangi (distant). (Box 3, Print 307)
  - Exit of the Shahur Tangi, (distant). (Box 6, Print 307, Page 47)
  - Exit of the Shahur Tangi (near). (Box 3, Print 308)
  - Exit of the Shahur Tangi, (near). (Box 6, Print 308, Page 48)
  - Looking towards Haidri Kach. (Box 6, Print 310, Page 44)
  - Picquet above camp Haidri Kach. (Box 6, Print 311, Page 46)
  - View from Haidri Kach picquet looking towards Sarwaki. (Box 6, Print 312, Page 50)
  - Looking towards the Sulieman Range above Sarwaki. (Box 6, Print 316, Page 51)
  - Daily convoys returning from Wana. (Box 6, Print 322, Page 49)
  - Daily convoys returning from Wana. (Box 6, Print 324, Page 52)
  - Rogha Kot camp perimeter, and Minchin Baba. (Box 6, Print 325, Page 43)
  - Village tower near Wana. (Box 6, Print 329, Page 55)
  - Wana Fort and plain. (Box 6, Print 330, Page 53)
  - Column encamped Wana Fort. (Box 6, Print 331, Page 54)
  - Wana Wazir hostages. (Box 6, Print 332, Page 2)
  - Character Study; Wana Waziris. (Box 3, Print 333)
  - Character Study: Wana Waziris. (Box 6, Print 333, Page 10)
  - Michni Road, Peshawar. (Box 5, Print 341, Page 12)
  - The Mall, Peshawar. (Box 5, Print 342, Page 11)
  - St. Johns Church. (Box 5, Print 344, Page 13)
  - The City Mission Church (Box 5, Print 345, Page 14)
  - Caravan Sarai, Peshawar City. (Box 3, Print 347)
  - Peshawar City in the main street. (Box 3, Print 354)
  - Silk market, Peshawar City. (Box 5, Print 355?, Page 15)
  - Attock Fort and Church. (Box 5, Print 370, Page 20)
  - Attock looking down the Indus. (Box 5, Print 371, Page 21)
  - Attock Bridge. (Box 5, Print 372, Page 22)
  - Kaur Bridge Fort. (Box 3, Print 385)
  - Manzai. (Box 3, Print 386)
  - Sararogha Camp. (Box 3, Print 392)
  - Camp Idak. (New view showing the fort). (Box 3, Print 403)
  - Isha Picquet with Waziri types on the Road. (Box 3, Print 405)
  - General view of Azad Khel, looking towards Razani. (Box 6, Print 407, Page 16)
  - Camp Azad Khel. (Box 3, Print 408)
  - General view approaching Razani, with camp in the distance. (Box 3, Print 411)
  - Camp Razani (Near). (Box 6, Print 412, Page 17)
  - Daily convoy entering the defile near Razani, showing the new road above and a tribal block house. (Box 3, Print 414)
  - A camel convoy in the snow. (Box 6, Print 418, Page 21)
  - Looking towards Razmak Camp with Pir Gul in the back ground and plateau covered in snow. (Box 6, Print 422, Page 20)
  - From the Narai towards Razani. (all covered in snow.) (Box 3, Print 423)
  - Camp Razmak. (Looking west). (Box 6, Print 425, Page 22)
  - Camp Razmak with Everest Picquet in back ground. (Box 6, Print 426, Page 23)
  - From Everest picquet towards Pir Gul. (Box 6, Print 429, Page 19)
  - From Everest picquet looking towards Bannu. (Box 3, Print 430)
  - Typical Mahsud and Waziri tribesmen. (Box 3, Print 431)
  - Typical Mahsud and Waziri tribesmen. (Box 6, Print 431, Page 9)
  - Character study "The Mahsud." (Box 3, Print 432)
  - Character study "The Mahsud." (Box 6, Print 432, Page 6)
  - Waziri types on the Tochi road. (Box 6, Print 434, Page 4)
  - The burning of Makin, Razmak Operations 1923. (Box 3, Print 436)
  - Bathing Ghats on the Ganges river-Benares (Box 3, Print 902)
  - Bathing Ghats on the Ganges river—Benares (Box 5, Print 902, Page 44)
  - The Taj Mahal and Jasmine Tower, Agra. (Box 5, Print 911, Page 45)
  - Taj Mahal, Agra, moonlight effect. (Box 5, Print 916, Page 47)
  - Taj Mahal, Agra. (Box 5, Print 917, Page 48)
  - Marble screen and interior, Taj Mahal, Agra. (Box 5, Print 920, Page 46)
  - View near Rampore. (Box 3, Print 1062)
  - Pahlgam. (Box 3, Print 1084)
  - Gamp Forest, Phalgam. (Box 3, Print 1084a)
  - The Liddars. (Box 3, Print 1089)
  - Club and Nedou's Hotel, Gulmarg. (Box 3, Print 1106)
  - The Khan of Dir welcomes the Viceroy with great pomp-the Panjkora river borders the valley with Hindu Kusk in the distance. (Box 4, Print 1420)
  - The end of the caravan crosses into Afghanistan from the Khyber. (Box 4, Print P.5)
  - Near Landi Kotal, Khyber Pass. (Box 5, Print P.10, Page 9)
  - A cold and misty morning, Peshawar Valley. (Box 5, Print P.14, Page 10)
  - Ploughing, the Kashmir homestead. (Box 4, Print UN-1)
  - Sind Valley, Kashmir. (Box 4, Print UN-2)
  - Dal Lake. (Box 4, Print UN-3)
  - Nanga Parbat 26, 660. The east aspect across the Astor River. (Box 4, Print UN-4)
  - Glacier Valley and campsite, Sonemarg, Kashmir. (Box 4, Print UN-5)
  - Return of Mohforce, Oct. 1935. New Road, Nahakki Pass. (Box 4, Print UN-6)
  - In the Sikkim Himalaya, view towards Darjeeling. The pony track winds over the ridges. (Box 4, Print UN-7)
  - The Indus. Baltistan. The pony track runs along the river bank. (Box 4, Print UN-8)
  - Untitled. Mountain and river scene. (Box 4, Print UN-9)
  - Open Road, Afghanistan, 1910. (Box 4, Print UN-10)
  - Looking towards the Lahore Gate, Peshawar City (Box 4, Print UN-11)
  - [A group of twelve men.] (Box 4, Print UN-12)
  - Caravans passing Ali Masjid, Khyber Pass. (Box 5, Print UN-13, Page 3)
  - [Street scene.] (Box 5, Print UN-14, Page 9)
  - Oabul (Kabul) River at Nowshera. (Box 5, Print UN-15, Page 10)
  - The Khyber Railway. (Box 7, Print UN-16, Page 1)
  - Bagiari Station at the mouth of the Khyber Pass. (Box 7, Print UN-17, Page 2)
  - Kafir Tangi Tunnel. (Box 7, Print UN-18, Page 3)
  - Near Fort Maude. (Box 7, Print UN-19, Page 4)
  - View from Changi Reversing Station. (Box 7, Print UN-20, Page 5)
  - Near Medanak Reversing Station. (Box 7, Print UN-21, Page 6)
  - Shahgai Station. (Box 7, Print UN-22, Page 7)
  - Ali Masjid Gorge. (Box 7, Print UN-23, Page 8)
  - The summit 3,500 feet above sea-level, Landi Kotal Station. (Box 7, Print UN-24, Page 9)
  - Near Michni Kandao. (Box 7, Print UN-25, Page 10)
  - Tangi Bridge. (Box 7, Print UN-26, Page 11)
  - Panorama on the way down to Landi Khana. (Box 7, Print UN-27, Page 12)